Guide to the Richard T. Gibson papers, 1948-2004 MS2302
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Richard T. Gibson papers
1926-2004
1948-2004
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gibson, Richard T.
MS2302
11.5 Linear Feet 23 document boxes
This collection contains correspondence, clippings, article drafts, and subject files collected by Richard T. Gibson from 1948 to 2004. Richard T. Gibson (1931-) is an American expatriate journalist, international correspondent, and author based in London. He is the author of African Liberation Movements (1972), was a member of the black expatriate literary community in Paris in the late 1950s, and was a founder of the Fair Play for Cuba Committee in the 1960s. He maintained active personal and professional correspondence from the 1960s to the 2000s, some of which contains information regarding leftist and anticolonial movements in the United States, United Kingdom, Europe, and Africa.
Biographical / Historical
Richard T. Gibson (1931-) is an American expatriate journalist, international correspondent, and author based in London. He is the author of African Liberation Movements (1972), which describes movements against white-minority rule across Africa, including South Africa, Rhodesia (Zimbabwe), Angola, and Mozambique. He worked as a reporter for the Philadelphia Afro-American, the Christian Science Monitor, Agence France-Presse, CBS, Revolution Africaine, Negro Press International, and Tuesday Publications, Inc. He was a member of the black expatriate literary community in Paris in the late 1950s, and was a founder of the Fair Play for Cuba Committee in the 1960s. He maintained active personal and professional correspondence from the 1960s to the 2000s, some of which contains information regarding leftist and anticolonial movements in the United States, United Kingdom, Europe, and Africa.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Gelman Library, 2012 (Accession Number 2012.015)
Arrangement
Organized into four series: Correspondence, Publications, Subject files, and Photographs.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, clippings, article drafts, and subject files collected by Richard T. Gibson from 1948 to 2004. The material was created and collected as part of Gibson's work as a journalist, publisher's agent, and activist, and includes material relating to liberation movements in Africa, and Marxist-Leninist and Communist parties in the United States, United Kingdom, and Europe. Individuals of note represented in this collection include Amiri Baraka, Julian Mayfield, Lyle Stuart, Jacques Verges, and Robert F. Williams.
Africa; African Americans; Journalism; National liberation movements; Gibson, Richard T.
- Correspondence, 1964-2003; Series 1; 7.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes personal as well as professional correspondence from 1964 to 2003, particularly regarding liberation movements in Africa, and Marxist-Leninist and Communist parties in the United States, United Kingdom, and Europe. In addition, some correspondence relates to Gibson's work as an agent of the U.S. publisher Lyle Stuart, and some involves the case of black nationalist Robert F. Williams. Finally, the series contains some personal correspondence between Gibson and his family. The correspondence in this series is primarily in English, with some in French and a small amount in Italian and German.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically, except for correspondence on a few specific topics and individuals, which are filed together by topic at the end of the chronological files.
  - Correspondence, 1964 September-December; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965 January-May; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1965 June-December; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1966; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1966 June-August; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966 September-December; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1967 January-March; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967 April-May; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1967 June-August; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1967 September-December; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1968 January-May; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1968 June-August; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1968 September-December; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1969 January-April; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1975 September-December; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1976 January-February; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1976 March-April; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1976 May-September; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1976 October-December; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1977 January-March; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977 April-August; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1977 September-December; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1978 January-May; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1978 June-November; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1978 December-1979 March; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1979 April-December; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980 January-June; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1980 July-December; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1981 January-June; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1981 July-December; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1982 January-May; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1982 August-December; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1983 January-June; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1983 July-December; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1984 January-May; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1984 June-December; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1985 January-May; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1985 April-July; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985 June-December; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1985 August-1986 March; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1986 January-August; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1986 September-1987 January; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1987 February-June; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1987 July-December; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1988 January-June; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1988 May-December; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1988 December-1989 March; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1989 April-November; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1989 December-1990 February; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990 March-July; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1990 August-December; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1991 January-May; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1992 January-May; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1992 June-December; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1993 January-August; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1991 June-December; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1993 September-1994 August; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1994 September-December; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1995 January-June; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1995-1997; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1995 July-December; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1995 January-1996 May; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1996 June-October; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1996 November-1997 April; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1997 May-September; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1997 October-December; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1998 January-February; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1998 March-June; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence -- Aftonbladet, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Amiri Baraka, 1975-1980; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Sandra Dixon, 2002; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence -- Evening Standard, 1988; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence -- Michael Fabre, 1987-2000; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- Roy Hodges, 1978-1986; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence -- Institute of Race Relation/OUP: "African Liberation Movements", 1973-1979; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence re: "Prelude to a Movement" documentary film, 2002; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence -- Irene Rose, 1956-1965; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with Emmett Steele, 1976-1982; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Lyle Stuart, 1969-1972; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Lyle Stuart, 1973; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Lyle Stuart -- FBI file, 1978; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence re: Robert F. Williams, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re: Robert F. Williams, 1967-1976; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and article on Robert F. Williams, 2002-2003; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence and documents, 1924-1956; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Family correspondence and documents, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence and documents, 1976-1990; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Index cards (contacts), Series 1 (Box 22)
  - Index cards (contacts by country), Series 1 (Box 23)
  - Index cards (contacts), Series 1 (Box 24)
- Publications, 1948-2004; Series 2; 3 Linear Feet
  This series contains magazine, newspaper, and newsletter clippings with articles by or about Gibson as well as materials Gibson collected on the subject of African liberation movements. These date from 1958 to 2004. It also includes draft articles and essays by Gibson, as well as early journals, which date from 1948 to 1954.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - The African Communist journal, 1999-2004; Series 2 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - African liberation publications, 1968-1973; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - African liberation publications, 1974-1988; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - African liberation publications, 1963-1994; Series 2 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Article drafts, 1965-1978; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Clippings [1 of 2], 1958-1996; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Clippings [2 of 2], 1958-1996; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1991-1999; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Clippings [1 of 4], 1968-2004; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Clippings [2 of 4], 1968-2004; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Clippings [3 of 4], 1968-2004; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Clippings [4 of 4], 1968-2004; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Clippings -- obituaries, 1998-1999; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Essay drafts, Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - "Friends of the Oppressed," or the New Bien-Pensants, 1984; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Gibson clippings, 1951-1955; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Gibson clippings, 1968; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Gibson clippings, 1970-1988; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Gibson clippings and reviews [1 of 2], 1972; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Gibson clippings and reviews [2 of 2], 1972; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Gibson clippings, 1983-1984; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Gibson clippings, 1984; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Gibson clippings, 1986-1987; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Journal, 1948-1949; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Journal, 1951-1952; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Journal, 1954; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - The Little Revolutionary, Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Press directories of London, 1971-1974; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Revolution Revue Mensuelle Internationale, 1963-1964; Series 2 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Tuesday Magazine, 1973-1975; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Robert F. Williams -- clippings, 1968-1969; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Zimbabwe News, 1967-1968; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Zimbabwe News, 1969-1972; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Subject files, 1965-2002; Series 3; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This small series contains administrative files, clippings, and legal documents that Gibson filed together by topic. It includes material on prominent anticolonialist Jacques Vergès, civil rights activist Julian Mayfield, and black nationalist Robert F. Williams, and dates from 1965 to 2002. The material is primarily in English, with some in French and a small amount in Italian and German.
  - African business, 1981-1988; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Baraka, Amiri, Series 3 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - FBI file -- Lyle Stuart, Richard Gibson, FPCC, Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Gibson biographical information, 1993; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Gibson v. Penguin Books Ltd., 1985; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Lisbon Conference Against Soviet Imperialism, 1978; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Malik, Michael Abdul, Series 3 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Mayfield, Julian, 1965-2002; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Swiss case, 1967-1975; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Verges, Jacques, 1967; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Robert F. Williams material for Ronald J. Stephens, 1969-2002; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 11)
- Photographs, 1926-1976; Series 4; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains photographs and slides of Richard T. Gibson, his family, and his travels. It includes family photographs from the 1920s to the 1970s as well as photographs from a visit to Cuba in 1960. Many early family photographs are labeled, but later photographs and slides are not.
  - Photographs, 1926-1955; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1960-1970; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Slides, 1960-1967; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Slides, 1972-1976; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Slides, undated; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 5)